Still
got to admit everybody. Yes.
All right. Good afternoon everybody. Uh
I just want to do a double check. Can
people online hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Thank you.
>> Perfect. Thank you. This is Dominic
Earllo at the Department of Health and
we're here uh right now with our hybrid
meeting for the propagation committee
with uh Chris Pascus as the chair and he
is here actually next to me and I'll
turn the mic over to him in just a
moment. But just a few usual reminders,
we do record this meeting and so we will
be recording it. Thank you to everybody
who is joining us online and thank you
to everybody who is joining us here in
person. Um, and uh, just as a reminder,
the main reason why we do not have
everybody visually on uh, camera is
because we do understand that there are
some people who live in areas that do
not have very good internet and we want
to make sure they don't drop off and
have to rejoin any more than they need
to. Um, and so that's part of it because
the video actually takes up a lot of
bandwidth and so that's why we typically
do not have people on video. Um, and
then the other thing is just because we
are recording this, please remember to
keep language uh, you know, appropriate
so that we don't have to bleep things
out. So even if you're doing things like
mentioning names of certain products,
some of them may not have appropriate
language in them for younger people. And
so please remember just to refer to them
then as either a product or uh, using
initials and that would be fine. And so
with that, I will turn the meeting now
over to Chris.
Uh thank you Donic and it's so good to
see some of you in person and thank you
for those of you who are attending
online too. Um as is kind of ritual in
this space. I always like to start out
with 30 seconds for us to to get
centered and to
um
just to remind ourselves why we're
coming to this space, why we're doing
this work and um to build a little
container of compassion for a world that
is uh see more than it share fair share
of crisis. So stay with me for 30
seconds please.
Um,
all right. So, I'm going to go around
and have uh everybody introduce
themselves here in the room first and
then we'll take introductions from
online. Um, remember if you uh want to
have a a a vote, if we do end up voting
on something today, you need to have
introduced yourself and be from New
Mexico. So, let us know who you are um
and where you're from and if you have
any affiliations, please
>> and you can actually just keep that one
on.
>> Yeah, just raise your hand if you'd like
this.
hi everybody. James Barrera from Ignite
Synergy. Um,
>> hello. My name is Eric Ba and I don't
have any resident and
Oh, then you can use it. They're pretty
weak mic, so try to talk like pretty
close to it. Hi, my name is Debbie
Meestas Trainer and I am a New Mexico
resident.
>> I'm Randy Trainer. I'm also a New Mexico
>> John Star, Mexico resident as well.
>> James Blackport out of Clovis, New
Mexico. I'm super excited about the work
that everybody's doing. Personally see
the benefits of this and super excited
to be a part of it. So, thanks everybody
for everything.
Uh, my name is Manny Grigo. I am from
New Mexico. I have no affiliations with
anybody, but I'm very very interested in
what's going on here.
>> Thank you everybody. Uh, at this time
we'll go to the online forum. If you'd
like to introduce yourself, please rej.
>> Okay, let's see. Looks like we've got
James Brown first.
>> James Brown.
>> James, you may unmute yourself. May
yourself.
>> Afternoon everyone. Uh, thank you Chris
again for being chair of this uh
propagation committee. James Brown.
>> James Brown.
>> I'm a doctor of pharmacy here in New
Mexico.
>> New Mexico.
>> Um, and I'm representing Five Degrees
North Healing Foundation, a nonprofit
organization.
>> I'm psychedelic facilitator trained in
psilocybin and I'm excited to be here
today and contribute.
yourself.
>> Uh, good afternoon everyone. This is
Stephan Hernandez, president of New
Mexicoology Guild and owner of New
Mexico. Thank you. Thank you.
>> Brett, you may unmute yourself.
>> You may yourself.
>> Hey, good afternoon everybody.
>> Brett Phelps from uh calling in from Las
Vegas, New Mexico today. resident in
Mora.
>> Um,
>> yeah, I'm I am an attorney, not
affiliated with uh with any
organizations. Just here to here to help
out and see what we can do to um get
this thing going. Yeah, I'm glad to glad
to be back. I've been real busy lately.
Missed a couple meetings and yeah, glad
to be back helping out.
>> Dr. Fatami, you may unmute yourself.
>> Thank you so much. I'm Dr. Lita Fetami.
I'm here with Conscious Physician
Psychedelics Academy. We are a local New
Mexican Academy teaching about
psilocybin uh mainly and we're in our
second no third month of our cohort
going uh strong uh for the next nine
months. So glad to be here and thank you
for all the work you're doing.
>> Stephanie Dukat, you may unmute
yourself.
Hi, my name is uh Stephanie Tukat. I am
um a grower up in Santa Fe. I own Santa
Fe Mountain Mushrooms and I'm interested
in the production side of everything.
>> Gregory Evans, you may unmute yourself.
>> Greetings. I wish I was there. I hope
you guys are all having a great time. I
am Gregory Evans.
I am an independent re researcher and
home micologist with no affiliations.
I'm based out of Santa Fe and my
intention is to support the program's
development through committee
recommendations aligned with emerging
research and best practices.
Excellent. Thank you all
uh for being here and uh thank you for
introducing yourselves and uh being part
of this process. It's it's awesome. And
we're going to go to some program
updates from
uh I'm sorry actually can you post the
agenda in the chat please? So today
we're going to get a program update.
We're going to talk about uh some of the
first rules that uh have come out of the
Department of Health that we're going to
uh start checking out. Um I don't know
that they've actually become regulation
yet, but it's a part of the process. I'm
sure you'll get that in the program
update. Um
and then we're going to make a little
time for further proposals for this
committee and then uh any discussion and
we'll talk about the next meeting. So,
uh, I'll turn it over to Dominic.
>> Yeah, you can use that.
>> Yeah, we'll just have the assessments.
>> So, uh, just so everybody knows, uh,
part of the process is that right now we
are working on writing and finalizing
the actual rule draft. So, we took the
recommendations from the committee and
we are converting them on over to the
rule draft. One of the sections that we
do have that's fairly complete and I
give this with the caveat is that there
still may be some minor changes before
we have to submit it to the uh registar
for final publication. Um now when I say
final publication that is for the rule
hearing. So even once we publish it or
I'm sorry I shouldn't say publish once
we announce it there will be a minimum
of 30 days uh before the rule hearing
itself. And so that'll be a public
announcement. We'll also send it out
through uh if you've signed up for the
e-news, we'll send it out through there
as well so that everybody is able to
read through and look at the full list
and the full set of regulations and then
people will have the opportunity during
that 30-day period to make comments uh
and actually if we miss something. So,
for example, even in uh in this version,
I noticed a typo. We got that fixed
already before we printed it. But you
know, things like that, if you see it or
if you say, "Wait a minute, that's not
what we determined and what we said. We
need to revisit this a little bit." This
is the opportunity to be able to do all
of that. Once the rule hearing occurs
and once that's finished, then what will
happen is the hearing officer from the
rule rule hearing will actually give us
a report back and it will include those
items of public comment. And so and and
the hearing officer will make
suggestions as to whether to adopt or
not adopt those particular changes or
different items. Um once that happens,
if there are no major changes, so for
example, say you all find out that I
misspelled psilocybin on every line, um
that's perfectly fine. We can make that
adjustment because it's simply a typo,
for example, or another minor
adjustment. And then the rule will be
what's called promulgated. Once it's
promulgated that means it becomes final
and it is in effect.
So um the timeline on this is we are
hoping to have this and have the
announcement before the end of March. We
are hoping to have the hearing um we
have it tenatively scheduled for April
24th but it depends exactly when we get
everything on in just to let everybody
know. Um, and so once that portion
occurs, uh, then everybody, like I said,
will be able to come and do that. It
will be we'll be holding it in Santa Fe
at the Department of Health. Um, and,
uh, and then you'll be able to provide
additional input. Um, and then once it
is promulgated and so it's finalized and
goes into effect, that's still not the
end of it.
And I know I've talked about this in a
lot of the meetings because what happens
is anytime you're starting a program and
you start implementing things, we do
find there are either errors, there are
mistakes, there are things that just
don't work really well. So we'll go
through a period of time where we will
be looking at that and looking at what
revisions need to happen and then
several months down the line um unless
we actually got it perfect the first
time, which I don't ever know of anybody
who's perfect, including all of us. So
um but if that happens and we we are
able to make changes, we will hold
additional rule hearings and adjust the
rules. So that's one of the big things
to remember. The other aspect to
remember is we have to do this within
the bounds of the statute. I know there
are a lot of times where people will say
things like, well, we would like to do
this, but if it's not included within
the what the statute actually allows us
to do, we can't write rules on it. And
so we also have to be very careful with
that. And so uh just to let everybody
know with propagation I don't really see
very much with regard to that. But there
are some other areas where people have
had questions and concerns. But like for
example we can't turn around and have uh
uh intra or interstate sources for
psilocybin. That means all the
psilocybin has to come from inside New
Mexico. So all the mushrooms for it need
to be grown in New Mexico. They can't
turn around and we won't be licensing
someone who's in Colorado to, you know,
grow in Colorado and transport it here.
They can't do that. And that's because
it's federally illegal. So we can't do
those sort of things. So there are going
to be some things where people don't
necessarily realize that. We understand
that. We're happy to explain it. We're
happy to go through it. We're happy to
have additional discussions as we move
down the road. And that's happened quite
a few times over things. So, um, does
that make sense? Am I explaining myself?
Well,
>> yes.
>> Okay. Questions or anything from either
everybody here or online?
>> Yeah.
Someone in Colorado wants to come here
to grow mushrooms. Is there a time
period that they have to be a resident
or anything like that?
>> So, we've actually had quite a few
discussions about that and it really
fits in under the constitutional uh
commerce do dormcancy clause in the in
the constitution where only Congress can
actually regulate um businesses between
states and that sort of thing. And so
our attorneys have said very clearly
that we cannot restrict it with regard
to New Mexico residents being here. And
so there is that aspect of it. However,
we are including in because we've gotten
some feedback and from some very good
attorneys talking about things like um
predatory financial uh interests and
things like that. And so we are
including that within the regulations
because we hear very clearly people have
concerns that they want to ensure that
this is by New Mexicans and really
focused on New Mexicans. And so that is
one aspect that we're trying to honor as
best as we can within those uh
restrictions. I hope that helps and
makes sense.
And so, I mean, I guess I'll just say it
now, but what people are seeing in front
of them here in person, and we're going
to be putting it up on the screen um
here in just a minute or so on the
computer, is we have a version, like I
said, a portion of what we've written,
which is actually about the permit
application requirements um that that
producers would have to submit to be
able to do. And um and so that actually
shows quite a bit. And in fact, James,
to your comment, the section nine
actually does include the sections about
things like dual ownership, not
transference of that uh actual control
and uh for example, nominee straw and
proxy ownership, which um you know is
more about, for example, you can't have
someone come in as a like a management
company and say that oh, we're going to
go ahead and we're going to make a
contract with you because you're a New
Mexico resident and we're suddenly
though going control everything and all
the profits and everything else from it.
So there are several things with regard
to that to be able to help with that
sort of thing. Um and so we have that.
Um and uh is that actually the next item
on the agenda,
>> Chris?
>> Um yeah, I believe it is. It is there
any else from the program we should
update before we get into this though?
>> Yeah, so before we do that um we've
already talked about the fact that the
governor has signed the uh the equity
fund portion and the research fund. So,
uh, that's $630,000
going to the equity fund. So, that's
fantastic and we'll be working on some
of that in the equity group as to the
requirements for it. And then, um, they
there was also 300,000 that went to UNM
and Dr. Leman's programs that he's doing
with regard to research. So, that's
going to continue moving forward. So,
uh, that's fantastic news for research
about psilocybin here in New Mexico. Um,
and then the other thing is, um, I do
want to, we've, we've mentioned her on
some of the meetings, but I'm going to
introduce her now, and she doesn't know
I'm doing it, but we also do have Leslie
Peterson, who has joined our team just
this last couple of weeks, and who is
our new senior compliance officer. And
we do also have our environmental
scientist, is going to be joining us
starting next week, and we'll introduce
him when he starts here, coming on out.
Um, and so other than that, the program
and and with our attorneys at the
Department of Health otherwise, we have
been focused on working on those
regulations. And so that's really where
a lot of our time is. So, by the way, if
anybody has gotten a delay in us
responding to an email or a phone call,
that's actually why our please forgive
us. We're trying to get this all done so
that we can get it out as soon as
possible. And part of the reason why for
that as soon as possible, I guess I
should have talked about this part
before as well is that we're looking at
this from a reverse timeline. If we're
saying that we're going to the first
patients in December, it really means
that we need to be uh permitting the
cultivators this summer. And so by doing
this with the rules, because it will
take some time even after the rule
hearing, um then what will end up
happening is we'll have an application
process. And that's why we're actually
sharing this part because we want to get
some ideas on it if we've got it in the
right if we're on the right pathway for
it. But we'll have that application
process so that cultivators can actually
start applying and laboratories as well
so that they then can start growing the
psilocybin mushrooms so that we have
them available for patients come
December. I hope that makes sense as
well.
>> Yes, thank you. Um and then I do have
one more question. I feel like the
propagation committee is probably going
to start meeting a little more
infrequently since we've gotten a big
chunk of this material out of the way.
Um, but what is going to be the next
priority and where can people shift
their attention and time resources?
>> Well, I do think that the propagation
committee will be able to back off on
the frequency of meetings somewhat, but
we are going to have that point where we
need to evaluate what the rules are once
they actually go into effect. So for
example, is it allowing for quality
cultivators, quality laboratories to
apply? Are we excluding people are or
organizations? Is it something that's
going to be valuable? So I do think
we're going to have that evaluation
piece, but that's going to be a little
bit down the road. Um and so I do think
that the next steps uh from a
cultivation and a laboratory standpoint
is going to be about you know once the
rules are promulgated and they go into
effect is going to be starting to do
that evaluation. Now on the other side
our next steps and our next set of rules
is really going to be about the
practitioners so the providers making
sure that we have the requirements what
education is going to be required. uh
that's going to be one of the next steps
and the other one is the patient
requirements. So what additional
requirements are there for those
individuals who are qualified. So for
example because it is a medical program
I know that in the um in that particular
committee meeting about patient
qualifications one of the things that
has come up and been presented is what
kinds of examinations need to occur to
ensure that that patient is indeed a
qualified patient. what kinds of records
are needed? And so, and again, part of
our purpose is we want to make sure that
it is appropriate and a safe program and
so that we don't want to put a lot of
barriers up, but we also need to make
sure that people are doing this for
medical reasons because it is not a
recreational program. But so, those are
the next two steps I would say. And then
after that, and and I should mention
it's not like we're just doing one step
at a time. they're happening in, you
know, parallel courses. But then the
next big one to concentrate on is going
to be the locations.
So what exactly do we mean and what does
the statute mean when it says this must
occur in approved locations? And so
we'll be talking about what do those
permits look like? What do people need?
For example, and I'm just putting it out
there because I've talked about it
before. You know, you don't want to
suddenly say, "Well, we're going to do
this in a location where there are no
bathrooms. If you're having someone go
on their journey for six or eight hours,
someone's going to need to use a
restroom. So, you know, we have to think
about things like that. It may sound
very simple and silly, but there are
other parts of it, too. Like, for
example, is it being done in a safe and
secure place? What do we mean by safe
and secure? That's where we're going to
need help determining some of those
areas. Does that I hope that makes
sense.
>> No, that's great. I appreciate it. Uh,
does anybody have questions about for
the program?
>> We actually just need to do it so it
comes out.
>> I just
>> question
Shane McDonald said, "Sorry, but I came
in a bit late. Do we have a date for
applying for cultivation for
cultivation?"
>> Uh, one second. We have a question in
person first here. Sound like as you
were going through this, you talked
about
um that specific committee will talk
about what's interesting me is who will
be they will determine who's qualified
to make that determination. Will that be
in that particular committee?
>> Uh it's a great question. No, that
committee is looking at the patient
qualifications itself. The um there is
the other committee that's looking at um
practitioners and uh you know as far as
what that is going to be because that's
going to be the education and training
piece and who is going to be able to do
the do the different aspects in the
different areas.
That's a great question though. Okay.
And Katie, what's the question online?
>> Uh Shane McDonald said, "Sorry, but I
came in a bit late. Do we have a date
for applying for cultivation?
Thank you. No, those dates aren't uh we
do not have those dates yet. We're
hoping that we're going to be able to
have those applications this summer. And
part of that will depend exactly on when
uh we have the hearing for the rules and
if there are major changes that need to
be made or if there are no major
changes.
>> Oh, do you still have the mic over
there?
>> Oh, yeah.
Do we have anyone else online while
we're transferring the mic?
>> No,
>> we do not.
>> We do not.
>> Thank you. Okay. Lastly, I'm sorry. Do
you perceive that working in a for
example like RLD for years was
paperbased turn things in and they
recently changed to web-based
application processes that are I think
managed out of state. Do you perceive
that you'll start off with something
more like the old model for them or will
it start out web- based and so on? Well,
I I'll I'll start with that because when
we started the program with Department
of Health for medical cannabis, uh going
online was not even an option and so we
had to start on paper. But we actually
were transferring over and uh we
actually had built the system to do the
online portals for applications before
the CRA went into effect and all of that
aspect transferred over to RLD. We just
hadn't been able to implement it because
of just that happening so quickly.
However, if you are uh or for anybody
who's a patient with regard to medical
cannabis, we've been online for several
years and we are not going back to
paper. Um if you actually ask anyone,
you'll hear me say that, wait, that's on
paper. Why do I have paper in front of
me? It really should be electronic. It
makes it a lot easier for review, for
edits if edits need to happen. If for
example uh say we go through an
application and you know like with the
permit and someone accidentally forgot
to upload a particular certification
that they needed we can review it and it
can be much easier for them to then
amend it and add that sort of thing. So
no we will not be doing paper um it will
be going through uh from that. Now I say
that with a caveat because the system
has to be built. So there is a small
possibility that the very first
cultivators may have to give us a little
bit of paper. But part of our goal is
that we will not be doing that and that
it will be all electronic.
By the way, to give you all an idea of
how much the electronic side really
helps our patient approval process, when
I moved back to medical cannabis in 2019
and we were still on paper applications,
we were at the statutory limit of 30
days to review applications because the
volume was so much and they were coming
in and there would be so much paper. I
mean, the amount the volume it was
crazy. We actually thought that the
floor wasn't going to support it at one
point, and I'm not joking about that. We
had to move all of our records because
the floor wasn't going to be strong
enough to support it. Um, but since we
switched on over to electronic, we now,
as of this morning, our processing time
from when someone submits an application
electronically averages
63 days.
And the reason it's that high, and I do
say that that's high to me, is because
if you submit it on a Friday afternoon
at five o'clock when our office is
closed, it's not going to be reviewed
until Monday. If we didn't have holidays
and weekends, we would probably be
within probably at less than 0.25 days
to review applications. Now, that
doesn't mean it's approved. That means
it's reviewed. So just as a as a
reminder, but that gives you an idea of
how much of a difference this makes. So
when we talk about this as far as why we
want to do it online, it streamlines the
process. And that's a part of why we
feel once the applications do open up
for um cultivators and laboratories,
that process will be fairly quickly.
Won't be less than a day, but it will be
pretty quick.
Anyway, I hope that helps. I just like
to illustrate with real world examples.
>> Great. Uh, all right. Are there any
further questions uh regarding the
program as a whole?
>> Um, I have some questions about
something specific, but I assume we're
getting that. Okay, then I'll get that.
>> Excellent. I don't see any more
questions online either. Um, so we had a
board meeting last week. I'm sure some
of you probably attended where the
proposals that we all came uh came up
with over the last couple months have uh
been approved unanimously through the
board. And so uh the Department of
Health has started making um rules out
of our recommendations and we're going
to get into the permit application
requirements portion of that now. Uh, so
can you is that already displayed
online?
Yes. All right.
Excellent. So, I'll just uh start
reading through these and we can stop at
each section and discuss as needed.
Um, permit application requirements.
Section A, general requirements. An
applicant for a producer or laboratory
permit shall provide to the department
and shall maintain the following
records.
One, business license in the state of
New Mexico. Two, proof of registration
with New Mexico Secretary of State.
>> We asking questions as you go along.
>> Uh, you want to read?
>> I would like to read through this
section and then we'll we'll talk about
that section if that works.
Uh, three, proof of registration with
New Mexico Taxation and Revenue
Department. Four, certificate of
occupancy. Five, proof of fire code
compliance. Six, electrical and HVAC
inspection reports. Seven, proof of
compliance with applicable city and
county planning zoning requirements.
Eight, proof that facility is within the
geographical boundaries of New Mexico.
Nine, proof of ownership of the facility
or written approval from the owner to
cultivate psilocybin on the premises.
10, conditional use permits where
applicable. For example, city of
Albuquerque raw food permit 11. At and
at test station that alls psilocybin and
psilocybin products will be produced or
tested as applicable to the permit type
only within the state of New Mexico and
will not be transported beyond the
borders of the state of New Mexico and
12. such additional documentation as the
department may reasonably request to
ensure doc ensure compliance with this
rule or other applicable laws,
regulations or ordinances.
All right. Uh now I'll open it up for
comments, please.
>> All right. Here's the mic.
>> Thank you. Um I think just clarity on
some of these um from Mike's
perspective. Um proof of registration
for what for
Secretary of State for business or
lobbyist or not very clear. So any
business needs to register with the uh
with both secretary of state and tax and
revenue and that's all that is needed is
that um that and so like the first one
for example shows business license in
the state of New Mexico and so you would
have to show that you have that business
license and then in addition to having a
business you still have to register with
both the secretary of state and with tax
and revenue for example. I guess follows
through. I think the Secretary of State
has multiple things that they regen you
for and it's not clear as to exactly
what it is you would be sending somebody
over there for.
>> And that's the business license aspect.
That's why that starts at the very top
and it follows through.
I get what you're saying. It's but
that's how that works when writing
regulations. You start at the top and
then it all follows down through. So in
this case, you would go and you would
obtain your business license. Then you
would show that you have registered that
business with the secretary of state and
then prove and show that you have
registered and have that registration
with New Mexico tax and ref.
>> I just again I don't think it's clear
but okay
>> and then I guess the other thing is on
number six um
I guess two comments here. Do we know
that local we're asking local
governments to do several things here?
Uh one do we know that they actually do
those things. Um, I've been surprised
before in rules that we've asked people
to do things and local governments say
we don't do those things. And so I just
want to make sure that that in fact when
somebody shows up to local government
and ask for an inspection report,
you know, like the uh electrical and uh
HBAC,
are we asking for a code inspection? Is
that what this is?
>> Yes. and for example, and so the
electrical and HVAC inspection is
usually done as part of that certificate
of occupancy. And so we're just asking
for that to also be provided.
>> Okay. Again, I just think this could be
clear. And then on items seven and 10,
it seems to me a conditional use is part
of a zoning code. The zoning codes are
structured in such a way that they have
special use permits or special
exceptions, I should say. special
exceptions. And special exceptions are
either variances or conditional uses.
And so it looks like you're mixing a
health permit, like a raw food permit,
with a zoning matter. And it just seems
confusing to me because a conditional
use is not for a food permit. It's for a
zoning action. So I just bring that to
your attention.
>> Okay. Thank you.
So, uh, when I'm reading through these
things like the CO fire code inspection
just mentioning, so I know many times
when you're going through these
processes for other types of permits
with the state of New Mexico and you're
out of a local municipality, whether
it's Albany or Santa Fe, they're phased
in, so to speak, you know, where you go
and you do a certain part of it with the
state. The state says you are in
Albuquerque. So then they go standby.
We're done with this part. We're going
to send that to this the city of
Albuquerque. I assume that's going on
behind the scenes like where so if I
live at you know if my business is going
to be at such address in Albuquerque
um Albuquerque also has to prove that
that's an appropriate use for that
address. So will it be similar to
previous programs say like alcohol will
those people talk to each other and the
city will get wrap up several of these
things in that process so they can
present us with something that then we
come back to the state and go here it is
>> yes and that's that's a part of the
application process to be able to go
through it remember this is just what
the requirements are going to be for a
final permit too deep in the permitting
is what you're saying instead of just
the rules
>> yeah well in the next step and that's a
part of What I was saying earlier is
part of the process may take a little
bit of time. What you're thinking about
is okay we go through this step. So for
as you mentioned so we say okay as a
state we have brought it to this level
we are saying that you're good so far or
you know you've submitted what you need
to now the city or the municipality or
county sometimes would say okay now that
you've got this you've made it this far
now we'll go out and do the inspections
on x y and z and do that and then we get
the information on back that's a part of
why doing it electronically is going to
be much easier than doing it paper.
>> Yeah, that's a great question.
>> Have a question in the chat.
Is there any way that we can get people
commenting in the room to selfidentify?
>> Oh. Uh
>> oh, yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, we'll So, uh in the chat,
somebody just asked whether or not we
can have people just say what their name
is uh when they're having a question so
they know who's talking. So,
>> uh, James Blackboard here. So, this is
just a general like maybe this can
happen. Um, I understand that different
cities whenever you um register your
business with the city, there are
certain requirements that's approved on
the local level as they may differ from
where you are. Would it be at all
possible because I know the Department
of Health isn't looking for more work,
you know, as far as like looking over
what's good and what's not. Um would it
be possible if like even four through
eight if one registers their business
with the city that all of these would
kind of be in the city's responsibility?
You know that that that would fall under
that. So it's just not something the
department of health would have to mess
with if the business was registered with
the city. I I don't know if that's
possible. It must work for you all.
>> And I appreciate that, James. Thank you.
This is Dominic, by the way, responding.
Um I appreciate that. The unfortunate
part is not all locations are within a
municipality or even fall under a
county. There are many unincorporated
areas. And so in order to also include
that aspect, we have to still do it for
everybody. But because those are things
that will be a part of that process, for
example, in uh when someone's going and
getting their uh fire inspection done,
for example, that'll be a part of what
they have to do. We're not asking them
to do additional work. they'll just have
to submit that as well.
>> Um, and again, this goes back to the
electronic version. We're not going to
have piles of paper sitting around to
actually potentially create a fire code
issue. So,
>> but I appreciate that because as we've
kind of said, if there's someone else
who's doing it and we don't need to do
that, then that's going to help speed up
the process. It's going to make it a lot
better and a lot easier. And so, I
appreciate that.
Okay. Any other questions? Do we have
any online?
>> No.
>> Nope.
>> Okay. Chris, do you want me to read the
next section?
>> Ask there is
>> Oh, as I asked. Okay. What?
>> Okay. Yeah, we've got one question
online. Let's see. Are these draft? And
this is Orion. uh are these draft permit
application rules or are these the
decided rules for the program and are
they available online?
>> So as I mentioned earlier these are
draft and once they are finished we are
going to be publishing them um and then
they will go through the rule hearing
where additional public comment can be
made.
Okay so section B. So Chris this is why
I chose section B. It's only a
paragraph. Uh, additional producer
application requirements. An applicant
for a producer permit shall additionally
provide to the department and maintain
food safety training certificates for
employees.
Any questions on that?
>> No, don't be sorry at all.
>> No, I'm not.
>> We're here.
>> Uh, Jake Blackboard again. Um, I assume
>> Oh, I don't think the mic is um
>> There we go.
>> There we go. Uh, James Blackboard again.
I assume uh in that statement it's
implied that um if you don't have any
employees, if you're just so sle
proprietor doing it, that you would
still be required for that. It wouldn't
just be because it's only one person. Um
and then I assume that would be a New
Mexico um food safety training
certificate.
>> There are actually several different
food safety training certificates. For
example, Bernalo County has their own in
a specific one if you're within Bernalo
County. Um, and so it really is any uh
applicable food safety training
certificate.
>> Okay. And this would be a food safety
training certificate because it seems
like isn't like food handling broken
down into different types of categories
or or would it be the same food safety
training certificate that say you're
serving food at a restaurant to this? It
would be the same. Okay. Okay. All
right. Well, thank you.
>> Okay.
And then we've got um Denali Wilson
online.
Let me go ahead and unmute you.
Okay. Denali, your mic is enabled. You
can talk when ready.
>> Hi everyone. And sorry I um am a little
I maybe this might be relevant to
section A if we're okay going back. um
back there. Sorry, I was slow to the
draw, but I was just going to make the
recommendation that on nine
um the proof of ownership of the
facility or written approval from the
owner to cultivate psilocybin that we
additionally have the option that um
that you that the cultivator provide
um
proof of permission through providing a
lease agreement just because I can
anticipate the owner of a property
premises being reluctant to explicitly
write approval for psilocybin
um for federal illegality reasons. Um so
we might not want to require that the
owner of the premises specifically
authorize the cultivation of psilocybin
but that that by providing um a lease
agreement that doesn't specifically
preclude that that that would suffice. I
just don't want to put renters in an
unfair disadvantage if they can't get
that written um specifically from the
the property owner.
>> Thank you, Denali. That's actually a a
great point except that we actually have
practical experience with that in the
past where with cannabis some uh owners
who were leasing out the land after they
found out what the purpose was from the
renter they shut them down. And so that
meant that those particular businesses
invested a lot of money to do something
that then they were just kicked out and
they had no recourse because it's
federally illicit. And so this actually
helps to protect the the renter if
they're renting that property by doing
that. I hope that makes sense.
>> Yeah, thank you so much, Dominic. I'm
going to think on it a little bit more
and um I'll circle back. I know that
this will be just one of many
conversations.
>> Okay. Yeah, looks like that's
>> okay. So, uh, I'll go ahead because I'm
not going to, you know, jip you on that,
Chris, and not read more. But, uh, so
part C, additional laboratory
application requirements. An applicant
for a psilocybin testing laboratory
permit shall additionally provide to the
department and maintain the following
records. One, a license permit or permit
from the New Mexico Regulation and
Licensing Department cannabis control
division with a proof of current
approval to operate as a cannabis
testing laboratory in New Mexico.
B, standard operating procedures for
sampling and testing of psilocybin and C
an initial demonstration of capabilities
for each of the tests required by this
rule or two proof of current ISO IEC7025
or NEAC/TNI
accreditation with A standard operating
procedures for sampling and testing of
psilocybin and B initial demonstration
of capabilities for each of the tests
required. ired by this rule.
And so essentially what this does does
is this pulls in the aspect that we
talked quite a bit in the committees
about having those different pathways um
with regard to if someone's already or a
business is already a cannabis
laboratory they already have the
equipment understand the procedures and
so it's a pretty easy switch for them to
add psilocybin or if they are not
currently and are not interested in
being a cannabis laboratory they have
another pathway using some of the
national accreditation pathways. Now
there's a third part which uh as we
talked to the attorneys we didn't really
need to add in this section and that was
that if it is the approved laboratory
for the department which is SLD uh state
laboratory division that they can be
utilized. Um but that as it was
determined didn't need to be in here.
Any questions concerns?
Give people a moment to read.
Okay. You want me to continue or I can.
It's up to you. You
>> sure? I am good. Uh so the next section
part D changes in location, equipment or
status. A permittee shall apply for and
shall obtain an amended permit prior to
implementing any substantial structural
modification to its permitted location.
Additionally, a permit shall notify the
department of any change to
registrations, licenses, permits,
certifications, and any equipment
alterations or acquisitions that
substantially affect the production
process.
So, say for example, they're changing. I
see a couple of people with questioning
faces. Uh, and I hope I'm going to
answer for the right portion. Say, for
example, somebody decides to switch over
in a portion of the production and
they're using a new piece of equipment.
They would need to submit to the
department that here's the new procedure
because it could potentially have issues
with regard to their processes for
contamination and other things and are
they actually setting that on up. Um,
it's really just to ensure that things
are being done safely and
cleanly, so to speak. Does that make
sense? And to give an example as far as
for structural, we did have, for
example, a a previous lency in um in the
cannabis program who they went in and
they actually made changes to their
building, did not get a new certificate
of occupancy, and they ended up actually
getting shut down at that time by the
construction division because it was
unsafe because they removed a support
beam.
So that's the reason for it. Um, not
that I anticipate or expect things like
that, but then again, you never know
what's going to occur. So, it's really
just comes from a safety standpoint.
>> And then we've got a hand up in the
chat. Um,
>> and so there's a hand in the chat.
>> Okay. Should be good.
>> Oh, okay. We're good.
>> All right, Greg, your mic is enabled.
Yeah, I think uh
>> yeah, I think um uh if you could mute
that.
>> If you could mute that.
>> Oh,
>> mic. Yeah, cool. Much better. So,
real uh just
first I want to say that it might be
worth having a trigger in here to have a
have a compliance review depending on
the type of change. Um, just to make it
super clear, like if we're putting in
reverse osmosis and changing the water
and that therefore need a building
permit to do that type of work or
whatever it is, like that might be
something that preempts like a check-in
point with compliance. But like for a
practical application, say I'm a small
company and I'm using a drill bit to
blend all of my substrate and I'm doing
it all by hand and one day I get a
massive substrate mixer. That would be
something that triggers a review and uh
compliance
uh certification. Yeah. Is that about
I'm understanding that correct?
>> Uh thank you Greg. Uh this is Dominic
again and um that's why it does say
substantially affects the production
process and so it's doing exactly what
you're suggesting.
Okay. And then looks like we've got a
comment in the chat um from Shane
McDaniel. Would adding more tents and
equipment to meet a demand but not
actual construction need to be approved.
>> Thank you Shane. This is Dominic and uh
if it's not changing the actual process
then that would not be something that
needs to be approved. Again this is to
substantially change the process.
I hope that helps.
Okay. Do we have other questions?
So when we talk about city permits and
all these sort of things and getting the
certificate of occupancies might assume
that like
it would happen at the level of the the
municipality about um for example say
someone was there's different sorts of
buildings different sorts of say perhaps
um manufactured housing manufactured
things that are under
equipment
Um, that'll all be settled out on what
the local municipality agrees that they
may or may not give a CO2 to.
>> That's correct.
So what if it's somewhere that meets all
of the criteria, sits in a safe and
legitimate space, but doesn't meet the
municipalities criteria of something
that is can obtain a CEO, yet it's more
under the would fit into say an
equipment,
for example, like shipping containers,
>> right?
>> It still would have to meet the
municipality or the local jurisdictions
requirements first. to to contain a
site,
>> right?
And that actually goes back to in the
other part it talks about must meet uh
where is it? Uh
that that's a part of the the question
that came up before with regard to uh
where is it? Sorry, I'm trying to look.
Yeah. Uh part seven, proof of compliance
with applicable city and county planning
zoning requirements. And then the other
portion about the conditional use.
Thank you Jorge for pointing me to
number seven.
Other questions?
Okay. The uh next part this is actually
section 7.35.2.9
general permittee requirements.
A compliance with applicable laws. A
permittee shall comply with all
applicable state, tribal, and local
laws, regulations, and ordinances,
including requirements concerning
agriculture, environmental health,
building and occupancy, fire safety,
zoning, and worker safety. Part B, dual
ownership prohibited. A person who holds
an ownership interest in a permit shall
not hold an ownership interest in any
other permittee.
Part C, permits non-transferable. A
permit shall not be transferred by sale
assignment or otherwise. A permit that
is transferred shall be invalid.
Part D. Transfer of actual control
prohibited. An applicant or permit
permittee shall not transfer actual
control of the applicant or permit
permittee to any person using a
management consulting or intellectual
property agreement or by any other
means. A transfer of actual control
shall invalidate an associated permit.
Part E, nominee, straw, and proxy
ownership prohibited. A person shall not
apply for or hold a permit if any
ownership interest in the permit is
nominal or without the benefits and risk
of genu genuine ownership or control.
Part F, record of financial interest.
Permittes shall create and maintain
complete lists of all individuals and
legal entities that hold a financial
interest in the permittee or the
operations of the permittee including
contact information for each individual
or entity and a description of their
financial interest. Applicants and
permadees shall provide the information
required by this section to the
department within 15 calendar days of
the department's written request for
such information. If a legal entity
holds a financial interest in the permit
or permites operations within the
medical psilocybin program, the
following individuals within the legal
entity shall also or shall be deemed to
also hold a financial interest. One, for
limited partnerships, each general
partner in the limited partnership. Two,
for limited liability companies, each
manager and managing member of the
limited liability company. Three, for
for-profit corporations, each principal
officer of the corporation, and four,
for nonprofit entities, each principal
officer of the entity.
And we'll pause at that point. That's
the end of that section
for questions.
All right. From Greg Evans in the chat,
he has suggestions
on B. He says, "Specify permit type as
producer.
Intention is to ensure that we don't
prevent producers from also being a lab
or other type of permite in the
program." And then F, he says, "Consider
including entity types unless
intentionally constrained, sole
proprietorships, general partnerships,
trusts, joint ventures.
um a sole prop is arguably the simplest
case and is not addressed.
>> Okay, thank you Greg. Um and I will be
honest, I am not a corporate lawyer or
someone from a finance law perspective,
but we will bring that back. Um, and and
just as a mention too, all of the
comments and suggestions will go back to
our attorneys to be able to review and
look at and see if there are things that
need to change, clarifications, those
sort of things. That's part of why we're
doing this.
>> Is there anything that you've seen so
far in the rules? I picked up on the
first part of the questions online that
prevents an entity of some sort from
being a pery as a producer and also
being a perman say a provider or
provider group. There's nothing to limit
that to prevent them in these rules that
I've seen with my credit.
>> So what it really comes down to is
anybody who is a permittee cannot be a
permittee in another aspect of it.
That's why the language is specific with
the permit. Um, and by the way, just so
everybody knows, the statute actually
says permits rather than licenses, which
is why the language throughout the rule
is about permits. Um, and so if I
accidentally say license, please forgive
me. 20 years of talking about licenses
and not permits, sometimes I make an
error. But um because that language
permites could be either laboratories so
they would receive a permit providers
receive permits and then also
cultivators receive permits. So with
this an individual can only hold one
permit
>> or or an entity
>> an entity correct. So in order to
operate in the realm of from A to Z
provide total service from patient from
beginning to end.
How you do that?
>> Well the cultivators would transfer the
product to the providers. Um they would
also be transporting or the laboratory
picking up um with regard to um doing
testing. Um but this is not a situation
because it's a medical program. You want
to ensure that there are those
separations because otherwise you could
have somebody who for example is
cultivating and then providing it to
patients who is not going through
testing.
And while we would like to think that
everybody all has good intentions and I
prefer to think that we also have to
prepare for individuals who may cut
corners as they look at things from cost
perspectives and things like that. And
so that separation is really there in
order to ensure safety and to protect
patients in the long run.
>> It brings up another question.
>> Can you introduce yourself again please?
>> Yeah, my name is John Star.
>> Um when you went back to the general
perittee dual ownership permitted person
who holds an interest ownership of
interest in perittee
just want to make sure I understand this
right. Um, so say myself, if I'm a
member of an LLC that applies and
obtains a permit to produce, I cannot be
the member of say another LLC that
requires a permit to be provided.
>> Correct.
>> I I think there's questions around that
just because um I guess that would come
up when we have the hearing, right? As
far as
>> you can bring them up now. Also
>> the main issue again is because of
potential conflicts of interest.
>> I I understand I also understand that
there's going to be there's people or
entities that want to in a legal way and
not participate in any conflicts say we
have this arm and that's our provider
arm what we do for patients. We have
this other arm where we grow and produce
and we also have this other arm that you
wanted to to be able to originate. Is
that all three of them or creating one?
>> That's all three, right?
>> Or they may just want two. They want
that they want to be able to help
patients over here, but they also want
to grow in that thing and go through the
legal requirements and maybe provide
that to their own provider entity as
well as other people's provider. But
what you're saying is that's not
possible.
>> That's correct. Because there would be
conflicts of interest with regard to
that because it could be problematic,
especially when it comes down to the
safety and the testing aspects.
over.
>> We need to just up hands up for a while.
>> Okay, let's see. We've got one hand up
online. Let me get back over here. All
right, so Denali Wilson.
>> Hi everyone.
>> Okay, mic. Yes, there you go.
>> Hi. Um, I just wanted to acknowledge um
I I can see, you know, I I know we had
some conversations in the interim um
with the department around potentials
for protecting against predatory
financing. Um, and I can see the origins
of that in this section. And so I want
to express some gratitude there. I just
want to be sure that we get it we get it
right and we don't unfairly
um
uh encumber businesses that um are
failing, right? And so specifically I I
want to talk about the transfer
provision. So it's the way that it reads
um can you scroll up whoever's doing the
share screen?
Um yeah, transfer prohibited. Um
I maybe maybe what it needs to read is
that the transfer is prohibited without
department approval, right? Because what
we don't want um is from a safety
perspective and from a predatory
protection perspective, we don't want um
this to be written like lending to be
written to transfer ownership um or if
if it is um we want people to know that
that's what they're that's what they're
agreeing to in a lending um in a
financing agreement. But I think from a
safety perspective, the department
doesn't want the permit to be
transferred without their permission.
Um, but if you know if somebody has
entered into a business interest and
that business is failing, we don't want
to require them to you know essentially
become bankrupt because they can't
offset that um that business interest.
So, I I I'm just wondering whether it
makes more sense to say that the
transfer requires department approval
rather than that there's no way, you
know, if if somebody has
um has entered into a cultivation
business and it's not no longer
financially viable for them, I don't I
don't think that we're protecting New
Mexico interests if we don't allow them
a way to sell that business. And I I
want to be sure that there's there's a
way for somebody to leave a business if
it's no longer financially viable.
Does that make sense? I kind of stumbled
through that.
>> Kind of stumbled through that.
>> No, thank you, Denali. Uh and this is
Dominic. Um that does make sense and I
understand exactly where you're coming
from. What it really is just saying is
that if somebody were to sell their
business, then the new owners would have
to actually apply for a permit. they
can't actually transfer the permit
itself. And that is in part because of
some of the issues, as I'm sure many
people know, that we've had with regard
to like alcohol licenses in the state
and how it's artificially increase those
prices. So, it's that the business can
be sold and the new owners can apply for
the permit, but uh it would not be the
permit itself that gets sold. So,
there's not a monetary value aspect on
the permit. I hope that helps.
>> It does. Thank you so much.
>> I'm going to take a couple comments
online.
>> Yeah, real quick. We got a couple
comments online. Um, let's see. Okay,
Shane McDaniel says, "What if any
permits would an integration coach
need?" Uh, Matthew Armstrong says, "It's
a great idea to keep all three
separate." Um, all right. Um, and then
Shane McDaniel again, uh, let's see. Not
allowing a sole proprietorship to have
more than one permit would interfere
with rural access to treatment is it
might be problematic to get enough
people to obtain permits for smaller
municipalities. And then Greg Evans
said, um, so what if I'm a cultivator or
a company that is a producer and I'm
permitted to do that work? Would that
mean that I would not be allowed to be
permitted as a facilitator or assistant
to ceremonial settings as a second job?
So, there's a few things there.
>> Yeah. So, uh and this is Dominic. So
those all pretty much cover the the same
item overall just about as far as the
permits and and the idea again on that
is because in experience that we've had
where permits were allowed um to be held
by the same individual in different
areas it invariably created issues and
harm and especially and that's something
that we especially have to keep separate
when we're looking at this with regard
to patients and so and Shane you had the
comment As far as in rural areas, that
is an aspect that we are looking at as
far as how do we ensure that that can
occur. But again, it does come down to
the aspect of you don't want to have the
same person necessarily growing it,
who's also testing it, who's also then
administering it. That creates conflicts
of potential interest and we need to
make sure that that that is not
occurring.
Let's go to this.
>> Yeah, my name is Eric. My name is Eric
Baka and I just wanted to comment on the
vertical integration is what you guys
are talking about. There's not going to
be vertical integration correct and so
as propagators that's another thing to
be thinking about is
because of the production
cost but also the value of the product
that you're producing um and there not
really being a set standard on those
amounts. the people potentially that are
going to be profiting here is the
provider in some form. You know, I'm not
saying that there's not profit for
propagation, but these are things that
need to be considered as well. If you're
not able to vertically integrate or hold
licenses, then um what the value of your
product you're producing and what you're
going to be selling it to a provider for
needs to be cons taken into
consideration. as far as like the value
currently of like street price or
whatever you want to say for silicon
mushrooms or whatever. It doesn't really
compute to being profitable
unless you have that figured out. So
like uh you know I'm just trying to tell
everybody that uh you know we were
talking about um or what was the state I
think Oregon one of the states their
maximum or what they did for 2025 was
what 15 kilograms. So if you think about
that financially uh that's like what 30
plus pounds a year. So that's easily
done in a month by a producer. You know
what I mean? Even with like a 12 25 by
25 or even smaller than that 12 x 12 you
could produce that amount. So I'm just
that's you know what I'm wrapping my
head around right now and trying to
compute how it's profitable for
propagation license. Um, and that's all
going to be, you know, we got to figure
those things out because like I said,
the even the providers, the providers
are dealing with what a medicalbased uh,
you know, uh, consultation, there's fees
that come in that that have nothing to
do with the product, you know, and
nothing to do with the scale of the
product. So, there's there's going to be
profits made on that. There's going to
be all those things, but what is a
profitation
uh, permit for, you know, how is it
going to be profitable for you? So,
those are things that are going to have
to be and maybe there's I don't know uh
a committee that kind of handles that or
whatever. I mean, that doesn't really
work for like capitalist reasons, but I
guess I don't know. These are things
that we need to think about though.
That's all I have to say.
>> There's there's other people online.
There other people online.
saying about you've had experiences and
this may result in some conflict of
interest but it appears to me I agree
with what you're saying the ability to
create your own market for your product
has been totally eliminated with this
potential conflict of interest that
seems to be handled by rules and
governance um to jump right to there
could be public interest so therefore
we're not doing it I think is just a
step too far in my opinion and the
ability along the lines of what you're
talking about to create your own market
good quality market where you do
participate in more than one arm I think
makes a lot of sense and that to
eliminate it by the potential conflict
is probably a little bit shortsided
should just be controlled with rules and
governance and make sure that it doesn't
happen.
I appreciate it and we will bring it on
back to uh the legal team. But um part
of what I can say and I'll I'll bring
this up as a scenario is I'm sure most
people are very familiar with regard to
our opioid crisis and what happened
quite a bit with regard to that is you
had people who were involved in both
manufacturing and creating the market.
And so the they were saying and pushing
that people take the opioids simply
because they had minor conditions causes
the issue that we have. And so I can we
can envision that you could have
somebody who is growing for themselves
and growing or I mean not for themselves
but for their own then company that is
then doing uh the actual um services and
doing providing therapy who are actually
saying hey we're going to increase our
number of patient load because then
we're going to be able to increase our
amount of production and that's that's
where the concern and that conflict of
interest comes. Now, do I want to think
that people would potentially do that?
No, I don't want to think that. But we
have seen that happen and we have seen
it in multiple industries. And so, we do
need to be very cautious with regard to
that. Now, does that mean that that that
there's not potential for that to change
down the road when we figure other
safeguards? Potentially, but right now
at this point, we have to look at it
from this needs to be the safest program
that we can actually implement. We need
to ensure that the patients who are
getting treatment are getting
appropriate treatment, that products are
tested, and that we're able to actually
move this forward in a way that ensures
that safety and doesn't create those
potential conflicts.
So, I completely hear you and
understand. Um, because from a financial
side, yes, it would seem as though, oh,
if we're if we're growing it and then
we're selling it to the patients, then
that would be a great way from a
financial standpoint, but it also brings
up concerns about safety. are then
because then for example someone may be
less inclined that if a batchet does
have contamination for them to actually
then dispose of the batch because they
put in that financial interest in
growing it and then they're potentially
providing that to patients or avoiding
testing in some way if they're part of a
testing laboratory. And that's why
there's that separation
and they are things that have happened
in many different ways in many different
industries. historically
been done and
back as the question
earlier
when I talked about the separate
committee and who that would be required
for the people that are able to say you
fall well potentially I say that's you
know depending on how that is
established whether someone that has to
hold a medical license or whether it's
like a nurse practitioner or whether
that level of education, there's already
systems in place statewide and federally
that hold them to a standard where the
same thing that happened during the
opioid crisis. I worked in pain medicine
for 20 years and they're held
accountable. And so those same
safeguards should be something that is
sensible enough to prevent those with
what we're doing here in this if we're
having the right level of requirements
for those people that say you're a
candidate. I mean, I think those people
are held to a very high standard,
especially if they hold a DF, a DEA
license, state medical license, or any
of those things. And I just sorry, I
just want to make sure that it's noted
in the record that those things should
be things that are in place already that
should safeguard us from those potential
conflicts of interest and not limit
commerce and not limit the ability to
treat this as a business move.
>> Thank you.
Thanks for um this is actually an easy
one. So I don't see it anywhere here,
but is there a cap on licensing?
>> Thank you. Uh there is no cap on it.
Anybody who is able to meet the
qualifications, submit the appropriate
items, would be able to be permitted.
>> And then uh we've got a couple comments
in the chat. Um, okay. From Shane
McDaniel, uh, did not get an answer to
the integration coach permit question.
Can we return to that? Okay, let me go
back to that. Okay, so, oh yeah, he was
just asking, "What if any permits uh
would an integration coach need?" And he
additionally comments, "Integration
coaches would never actually be in
contact with the medicine, so I would
not expect them to need a permit."
Thank you for the question, Shane. Uh
this is Dominic and um again, part of
that has to be determined um still by
the education and training committee as
to what exactly those requirements will
be, but um I do believe that you're
correct as far as an integration coach
or a guide most likely would not have a
permit. Um but again, that has to be
determined by that particular committee.
Do you have additional questions?
>> I don't see any more hands up online.
>> Cool.
>> Okay. And then the last section that we
have today is uh the general producer
requirements.
Um and this is section uh 7.35.2.10.
A producer shall only one only
cultivate, manufacture, and possess
psilocybin and psilocybin products on
the producers's permitted premises and
shall not transport psilocybin outside
the state of New Mexico. Two, use
equipment counters and surfaces for
post-h harvesting processes that are
food grade and do not react adversely
with any solvent being used.
Three, construct and maintain floors,
walls, ceilings, counters, and surface
areas in a manner that reduces the
potential development of microbials,
molds, and unintended fungi.
Four, maintain the licensed premises in
a manner that is free from conditions
that may result in contamination of
psilocybin products and that is suitable
for safe and sanitary operations.
Five, store all psilocybin products in a
secured locked area, including
psilocybin products that require
refrigeration.
Six, associate every harvest lot,
homogenize lot, and product lot with a
unique identification number and enter
this information into the traceability
system.
Seven, only sell psilocybin or
psilocybin products to other producers
and to practitioners and only otherwise
distribute psilocybin or psilocybin
products to medical psilocybin testing
laboratories or to department employees
for testing in accordance with this
rule.
And then eight, immediately discontinue
operations and notify the department in
the event of an imminent health hazard
that could result in contamination of
psilocybin products. And that's the end
of that section. So, are there questions
or concerns,
comments?
And of course, we'll pause for a minute
so people can digest it.
We do have a comment online.
All right. Um, Gregory Evans says, "Um,
but we have robust and rigorous chain of
custody as well as testing that would
mitigate those risks. If the permites
had separate business licenses, the
product would have to be tested and
transferred by record to be in
compliance. I respect the intention
regarding manipulation of the market,
but it all just seems manageable on this
scale. I will concede to the committee,
but it's alarming to me.
>> Thank you, Greg.
>> Do we have other comments or questions?
>> My name is Randy Trainer. Just a
question. When these uh rules go out for
public comment, are these sent to uh tax
and rev secretary of state, municipal
league, association of counties,
construction industries division.
>> So they're put out publicly and uh yes,
the it does go out through the register,
the New Mexico register, which also
contacts those various agencies.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Okay. Any other questions or comments?
Uh, Manny Grigo. Uh, I just had a
question on number seven. Only sells
psilocybin or psilocybin products to
other producers and practitioners. So,
does that mean
if I'm a producer, I can sell liquid
culture to another producer or share
those kinds of things? That's just kind
of
>> Yeah, that's a great question. And the
answer is yes.
>> Okay. Any other questions, comments?
Okay. Well, thank you everybody.
All right. So, uh, having got through
that, we have another meeting here next
week in Santa Fe where I'm assuming, uh,
we're going to get another drop of draft
regulations that we're going to go go
over. Um, but I'd like to open it up uh
at this time for any anything that you
know we made our initial
recommendations, but has anybody thought
of anything that we may have missed or
need to address any gaps?
Oh, and just real quick, I'm just going
to read a comment in here.
Uh, there's just two comments in here
real quick. Um, Orion says number four
seems very broad. Uh, that's the
maintain license premises in a manner
that's free from conditions part. Um,
uh, let's see. Seems very broad. What
standards are we asking producers to
uphold specifically?
And then Shane says, "Regarding liquid
culture, can that be purchased across
state lines?"
Uh as far as for the first part with
four, there's actually uh another
section that's being developed that goes
into those details a little bit more.
That's just the general aspect of it. Um
and then as far as that the liquid
culture, um you'd have to look a little
bit more at the federal law on it. Um I
am not sure because my understanding is
that um spores are not necessarily um
problematic, but I do not know the
answer to that myself. perhaps Denali.
Um, if you're still on, maybe you know
the answer regarding that, but with
regard to the regulations, we'd only be
looking at internal to New Mexico.
>> Let's see. Denali, do you happen to
know? I see your mic is still enabled.
Okay, she does not know.
>> Sorry.
>> No, you're good. All right, moving on.
There is
>> we've got there was an answer right
after the no.
>> Oh, there was an answer. Okay. Uh, it's
okay. Yeah, Shane McDaniel, it's
currently legal to purchase across state
lines. All right. Thank you.
Okay. And we had an inperson question.
Perfect.
>> James Blackboard here again. Um, so I
mentioned it before and this may not be
established. I know there's so many
different arms to this thing as it's all
kind of forming, but um from the
cultivator standpoint, I think New
Mexico is going to be different than the
other two states because we're requiring
the end product to be homogenized and I
don't think it's like that in the other
states. Correct. Um so with it being
homogenized, you know, obviously it has
to go in some type of capsule form or
whatever. So just mentioning you know
the the standardization of you know
quantity sizes u requiring different
equipment and stuff like that to
encapsulate the product um if there is a
conversation on that still kind of
happening in the background.
>> Thank you James. Um that's a good
question and I think a lot of that is
going to depend on the dosage and there
is the committee that is talking about
dosage at this point but we're not
putting in a specific size limit on it.
So for example uh if it ends up the
dosage is twice the amount of say you're
putting it into a gelatin capsule then
it would be the individual would take
two for example. So we're not limiting
as far as that size. We're not getting
into that kind of detail with regard to
the manufacturing side. I hope that
helps.
Yeah, I guess it's the it's the
increment.
Sorry.
I I guess it's it's the increment of it
because if it's going in, you know, 20
or 25, um, you know, that will be a
difference in, you know, the size of
capsules to get, you know, just the
density, stuff like that. That's all,
>> you know, and I completely understand on
that, but that again is going to come
down to what the dosage committee
determines would be the recommended
doses. So, I don't have an answer on
that because they haven't determined
that yet.
Oh, and and I should mention that also
allows for, for example, satchets. So
for example uh while that aspect is
being done if there was a cultivator for
example who does not want to buy that
equipment to do the encapsulating
portion or pill presses that sort of
thing they could do it just in satchels
which can easily be at the
administration could be used as te's and
in that sort of methodology so just to
give you an idea because we did have
that I remembered it was oh two or three
months ago we had that conversation but
I couldn't tell you which committee
>> so yeah but thank you. Will you remind
me of the dosage committee on Monday?
>> Oh, and yeah, for those who aren't
aware, the dosage committee is meeting
virtually on Monday. What's the time
frame on that one?
>> 9:00 a.m.
>> at 9:00 a.m. So, so if you have interest
in that part, I would suggest joining
in.
>> All right, we've got a question in the
chat. Priscilla Smith says, "Uh, what
constitutes a lot? Is that specified
elsewhere? Is there a weight limit?
>> Okay.
>> Um, thank you very much. Um, that is
going to be elsewhere. Um, the, um,
we're using the term there's batches and
lots, but essentially the homogenized
batch is essentially going to be the one
kilogram. Um, it is written a the way
we're looking at it is we're writing it
slightly different just because it's
more about testing, but it will be that
one kilogram will be that marker if that
makes sense. So what the what the
committee said is that a batch will be 1
kilogram of homogenized product. So
dried and homogenized.
So are you
are we just changing the term to lot for
the purposes of the the program? Okay.
Dominic shaking his head. Yes. assuming
that
um any further uh gaps or things that we
need to address on the propagation side
that people can think of.
All right. Um we can move to any
discussion uh topics that we haven't
already talked about
um
in regards to this or I'm willing to
open it up to other aspects of the
program although we can't really uh
speak on behalf of other committees.
All right. With uh no further questions.
Oh, wait. We have something online.
>> Uh yes.
Okay. Yes, we've got one hand up.
Priscilla Smith.
And I have allowed your mic. You can
unmute when ready.
Hello. Um, my name is Chrisa Smith and I
am with him with Crystal Clear
Analytics, which is a cannabis testing
laboratory here in New Mexico. I don't
know if it's mentioned here or somewhere
else, but I'm just wondering if other
products are going to be tested besides
the raw form. Um, there would need to be
a batch size on that as well. Uh, so
people understand the limits.
uh of their product, how far that CMA
extends to their product, if that makes
sense.
>> Yeah, thank you, Priscilla. Um the only
other testing that we were discussing
through the committee and was
recommended was that um if products were
sitting on the shelf for too long, then
they would need to be retested at that
point in time.
and and within the rules we had talked
about when testing occurs uh and please
forgive me because I don't have that
aspect right in front of me but I
believe it was two to five grams
uh was that correct or 2 to four grams
yeah my apologies I without it right in
front of me I don't recall but it it's
about 2 to five grams required for the
testing and part of that will be
determined by the laboratory's SOP so
for example if you only as a laboratory
would only need two grams you could pull
just that two grams for that testing.
>> I hope that makes sense.
>> That does make sense. I think what I'm
talking about is the batch size of
products. So for cannabis, I don't know
how this transfers to this industry, but
for cannabis, there's edibles, there's
concentrates, and there's flour or plant
material. And the batch sizes are
needing to be defined for each product
that needs to be tested.
So one CFA works for one kilogram of raw
material was what you're saying. Um but
I just want to make sure that transfers
into other products that batch sizes are
defined somewhere for those other
products.
>> Thank you. And yes, it's only the
homogenized product that's going to be
available. And they the only way that
can be distributed at this time um uh as
part of the recommendation is either um
through satchets or pills or capsules
that are created from the dried uh
homogenized batch and that batch being
the 1 kilogram.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
Uh Eric here again. Um I just wanted to
recap because I wasn't quite I missed
one of the meetings and were we still at
an impass on micro dose because of not
being able to go to only be able to use
it in approved facility. would that
still be aid or
>> so for the initial portions of the
program we are not looking at micro dose
and the main reason again is because
there are other aspects that need to be
determined and need to be developed
that's going to take longer than this
initial roll out in December and again
the main reason why is the statute also
states that there must be the uh the
preparatory session the administration
and then the integrative afterwards and
that it must occur in the approved
locations. Okay. So, as we roll the
program out, we determine other ways to
ensure safety and all of those things.
There's that possibility, but we're not
ready to start going into those details
at this time. Um, but again and again
because we don't have them uh because
we'll have to determine what those will
be and doing that within the structures
of the statute.
>> Thank you.
All right. And we got a question in the
chat um from Shane McDaniel. Would
probably need A and B samples. So if two
grams are needed for a test, producers
would need to send four grams, right?
>> Thank you, Shane. Again, that would
depend on their uh their procedures for
the particular laboratory. Uh but yes,
that's correct. So if they are looking
at needing to take multiple samples at 2
grams each, that would make four grams
in the sample. And it's part of why we
included that as a range, so that there
would be that flexibility and ability to
do those multiple tests as needed.
Other questions?
All right, with no other questions,
we'll go ahead and bring this
um meeting to a close. And our next
meeting will be in Santa Fe on the 18th
at 3 p.m. And Johnny, will you tell us
what our venue is?
>> Yes, it is the Gary Kurthers building.
and Gary is spelled in a different way
than you've ever seen it before. So,
just know that the way it's spelled on
the site is correct. Um, but yeah, and I
actually forget exactly where that is,
but it's the Gary Kather's building and
it's on the website.
>> And I'm not going to set up any
propagation committee meetings
uh past that uh for a little while until
we uh get some more rules probably uh or
uh drafted rather for us to take a look
at. Um, but we'll set up another meeting
probably at the conclusion of that. So,
thank you all again for your attendance,
for your work, for your attention, and
uh I appreciate you all so much.